<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Shijith.com</title>
    <subtitle>Random thoughts and musings</subtitle>
    <link href="https://shijith.com/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://shijith.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2023-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://shijith.com/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>What are the hottest panchayats in Kerala?</title>
        <published>2023-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://shijith.com/blog/kerala-panchayat-temp/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://shijith.com/blog/kerala-panchayat-temp/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story looks at rural Kerala and how it&#x27;s heated up over the last 10 or so years.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysis of satellite data shows that in the afternoon, the hottest panchayats tend to be in central Kerala, namely the districts of Ernakulam, Thrissur and Palakkad. A panchayat named Vadakarapathy in Palakkad is the hottest on average.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if we compare recent temperatures to 10-plus years ago, panchayats in southern Kerala, namely the districts of Kottayam, Kollam and Thiruvanthapuram have heated up the most. Vijayapuram in Kottayam district recorded the biggest rise in temperature.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aggregating figures at a state level, 55% of Kerala&#x27;s panchayats have grown hotter by over half a degree celsius in the last 10 years or so.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also investigate Vadakarapathy and Vijayapuram using various kinds of satellite data to find out what&#x27;s special about them. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;kerala_sun.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The sun looming over Chinese fishing nets in Kerala&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;The sun looming over Chinese fishing nets in Kerala. Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;flic.kr&#x2F;p&#x2F;at87Ho&quot;&gt;Tim Moffatt&#x2F;Flickr&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-i-m-doing-this-blogpost&quot;&gt;Why I&#x27;m doing this blogpost&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kerala is ridiculously hot, so hot that &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;Kerala&#x2F;comments&#x2F;zafi01&#x2F;comment&#x2F;iylmttd&#x2F;?utm_source=reddit&amp;amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;amp;context=3&quot;&gt;some wags&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; say the state only has two seasons—&#x27;dry&#x27; summer and &#x27;wet&#x27; summer. I can personally attest to how much warmer Kerala has gotten over the years, most likely an effect of urbanisation and development. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Higher temperatures are a problem because of how it affects your quality of life. It makes it tougher for you to focus on your studies or work, and if you have air conditioners, you have to operate them at colder settings, running up your electricity bills.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blogpost is an attempt to quantify how hot things are at present and get a rough idea of how much worse things have gotten over the years.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I focused on rural Kerala because I live in a village myself, and so does 52 percent of the state&#x27;s population. City dwellers and their problems get enough attention as it is from governments, academia and the media, so I wanted to correct for that. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve chosen the panchayat as the unit of study, because it represents the lowest level of government, and hopefully the findings here will spur village authorities into action by taking steps to bring temperatures down and improve livability. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-we-analysed-the-temperatures&quot;&gt;How we analysed the temperatures&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temperatures of panchayats here are determined from satellite data. Instruments named &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Moderate_Resolution_Imaging_Spectroradiometer&quot;&gt;MODIS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; aboard two NASA satellites detect the radiation emitted by a surface, and from those readings surface temperatures are estimated for every square kilometre of earth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These NASA satellites pass over Kerala 4 times daily—11:10 am, 2:10 pm, 11:10 pm and 2:10 am approximately. So we get 4 different surface temperature estimates in a day. We will just consider a single temperature, the one for 2:10 pm because that will be closest to the maximum for the day (which is when people feel the most discomfort). &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temperature for every square km within the territory of the panchayat is taken and averaged to arrive at a figure for the panchayat itself. We calculate panchayat temperatures for every day over five years and then average them to get a representative temperature for that five-year period. We consider two five-year periods in our analysis: 2018-2022 and 2008-2012.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Am averaging over five years instead of taking a single year just in case that year&#x27;s figures are anomalous in any way. Taking the most recent five years gives us a more accurate idea of what a place&#x27;s temperature profile is.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- METHODOLOGY GRAPHIC  --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;01_method_explanation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graphic roughly explaining method used to calculate panchayat surface temperatures&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;hottest-panchayats-over-recent-years&quot;&gt;Hottest panchayats over recent years&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We first look at the hottest panchayats over the past five years, 2018 to 2022. When we map things out, we see the hottest panchayats are around central Kerala (Ernakulam, Thrissur and Palakkad districts) and parts of northern Kerala. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;02_hottest_panchayats.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graphic Of Kerala Showing Hottest Panchayats of last 5 years, from 2018 to 2022&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we separate just the panchayats with average surface temperatures over 35°C, three of them are in Thrissur district, one in Ernakulam dist. and four in Palakkad, including the hottest, Vadakarapathy. It has the highest average daily temperature—36.3°C over the past five years. So what makes it the hottest?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-is-vadakarapathy-the-hottest-panchayat&quot;&gt;Why is Vadakarapathy the hottest panchayat?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out what makes it so hot, we divided it into areas of 1 sq. km each, to see which parts are to blame. In the graphic below, the hottest squares are circled in black.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;05_vadakarapathy_sat_data.png&quot; alt=&quot;A look at Vadakarapathy Panchayat through various forms of satellite data&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at those circled areas in true color, it&#x27;s evident there isn&#x27;t much vegetation there. And land use&#x2F;land cover data for 2021 tells us it&#x27;s a mix of cropland (orange in the graphic), trees (green) and built-up structures (red) on that piece of land.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the news stories I&#x27;ve been reading, Palakkad &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.newindianexpress.com&#x2F;states&#x2F;kerala&#x2F;2020&#x2F;mar&#x2F;20&#x2F;sizzling-at-41%C2%B0c-palakkad-dist-reels-under-heatstroke-threat-2119044.html&quot;&gt;gets pretty hot&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; usually. And on Vadakarapathy in particular, reports say the panchayat is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.newindianexpress.com&#x2F;states&#x2F;kerala&#x2F;2015&#x2F;mar&#x2F;22&#x2F;Open-Ponds-Driving-Change-in-Water-Scene-in-Palakkad-731697.html&quot;&gt;prone to drought&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, people get their water from tankers here, which is unusual for a Kerala village. And that because of the shortage of water, farmers have even &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.newindianexpress.com&#x2F;states&#x2F;tamil-nadu&#x2F;2015&#x2F;apr&#x2F;07&#x2F;3-Palakkad-Panchayats-Await-Chandys-Nod-to-Extend-Canal-739157.html&quot;&gt;abandoned farming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So even though land use&#x2F;land cover data has categorised much of the land in the circled area as cropland, my suspicion is that there isn&#x27;t much more farming taking place there. So the land use algorithms still identify the land as cropland because of the shape of the plots etc. but it is effectively barren. And barren land gets very hot and shows up darker in temperature grids.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just speculation though. If the story gets picked up by a media publication, I&#x27;ll look into it further and ask some academic or expert to provide more insight.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;panchayats-that-have-heated-up-the-most&quot;&gt;Panchayats that have heated up the most&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see which panchayat&#x27;s temperatures have changed most from the past, we compared the average surface temperature over 2018-2022 to another five-year period in the past, 2008-2012.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results show it&#x27;s the panchayats in southern Kerala—namely Kottayam, Kollam and Thiruvanthapuram districts—whose temperature profile have changed the most. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;03_hottest_panchayats_DELTA.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graphic Of Kerala Showing Panchayats whose avg. temp. has risen most from 2008-12 to 2018-22&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The panchayat that has heated up most is Vijayapuram in Kottayam, whose average daily temperature increased by 1.7°C (from 32.3°C in 2008-12 to 34°C in 2018-22). So what&#x27;s led to this rise in surface temperature? &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-has-vijayapuram-heated-up-most&quot;&gt;Why has Vijayapuram heated up most?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out what human interventions could&#x27;ve changed the character of Vijayapuram, we divided the panchayat into areas of 1 sq. km each to see which sections have heated up the most. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those sections have been circled in black in the graphic below.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;07_vijayapuram_sat_data.png&quot; alt=&quot;A look at Vijayapuram Panchayat through various forms of satellite data&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the graphic, comparing true color imagery from past and present doesn&#x27;t really give us an insight into what&#x27;s changed. The land use and land cover comparison gives us a better idea of what&#x27;s happened with cropland in the circled areas being replaced by built-up structures (homes, complexes etc.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zooming out and situating Vijayapuram in its broader geographical context clears things up a little. We see that the circle on the left is just 5 km from Kottayam, an important urban centre in Kerala.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening of Vattamoodu bridge &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=iwuOX540mUQ&quot;&gt;in 2016&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; across the Meenachil river has made them even more connected and possibly led to increased urbanisation of the circled area on the left. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;08_vijayapuram_surroundings.png&quot; alt=&quot;A look at the spatial context, the surroundings of Vijayapuram Panchayat&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Development in circled area on the right—and increased surface temperature—may be a response to the presence of Manarcadu junction, the hub of neighbouring panchayat Manarcadu, being inside Vijayapuram borders. In fact, Manarcadu&#x27;s own gram panchayat office is at the junction too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Manarcadu junction would&#x27;ve been around earlier too, and if that&#x27;s the case, it doesn&#x27;t really explain what has changed and what has led to this increase in development—and surface temperature—from 2008-12 to 2018-22.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I should stress this is all just speculation and I&#x27;ll investigate more if a publication picks this up.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-things-look-at-the-district-level&quot;&gt;How things look at the district level&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interesting exercise would be to see things in a bigger picture than individual panchayats, and check how Kerala&#x27;s rural areas are heating up at a district level. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do this by looking at what percent of a district&#x27;s panchayats have had their average daily temperature rise by more than 0.5 degrees celsius—0.5°C being the threshold of what could be considered a significant increase. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data shows that for the state as a whole, 55% of Kerala&#x27;s panchayats have grown hotter by over half a degree celsius in the last 10 or so years.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;04_districts_most_panchayats_heated_up.png&quot; alt=&quot;Kerala&#x27;s districts ordered by the percent of panchayats whose avg. surface temp. has risen by 0.5 plus degrees&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the southern Kerala districts of Pathanamthitta, Kottayam and Kollam, over 90 per cent of their panchayats have seen the average daily temperature rise by at least 0.5°C from 2008-12 to 2018-22. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temperature profile of southern Kerala changing like this most probably reflects larger shifts in the character of those places (less rural, more urban). &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;side-notes&quot;&gt;Side notes&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caveats, doubts and other random thoughts I couldn&#x27;t fit into the copy above. (I&#x27;m done with my story, so you can stop reading here if you want, just doing some housekeeping from this point on.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-satellite-data-instead-of-weather-station-readings&quot;&gt;Using satellite data instead of weather station readings&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why am I using satellite data for this project, figuring out temperatures of a place from hundreds of kilometres up in the sky, instead of using data from instruments closer to the ground? &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well it partly has to do with the granularity I can get. With a satellite, I can get the surface temperature for an area as small as a square kilometre. Combine a few of them and you can get the temperature for a whole panchayat. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we can&#x27;t do that with readings from weather stations, because of how few weather stations there are in Kerala compared to panchayats. There are 941 panchayats but only &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;aws.imd.gov.in:8091&#x2F;state.php?id=KERALA&quot;&gt;around 100&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; working weather stations in Kerala, so if you&#x27;re looking to get panchayat-wise temperatures, you&#x27;re out of luck. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it makes more sense to use an indicator like land surface temperature which we can calculate for every panchayat.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-surface-temperatures-instead-of-air-temperatures&quot;&gt;Using surface temperatures instead of air temperatures&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One issue with using land surface temperatures is that it doesn&#x27;t sync with what people normally understand as temperature. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What people think of as temperature is usually measured in the air 2 metres above the surface, while satellite data gives us the temperature of &lt;em&gt;the surface itself&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of enough weather stations to construct panchayat-wise temperatures has already been mentioned.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An alternative is to use historical 2m air temperature data from the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cds.climate.copernicus.eu&#x2F;cdsapp#!&#x2F;dataset&#x2F;reanalysis-era5-land?tab=overview&quot;&gt;ERA5-Land&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; dataset. This is a reanalysis dataset that combines actual observations and estimates.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERA5-Land being a reanalysis product would&#x27;ve still been acceptable for our purposes, but for the poor resolution of the dataset, around 9 km. So a single temperature from that dataset will be for a 9 x 9 or 81 sq km area. But 81 sq km could comprise multiple panchayats as a majority of Kerala&#x27;s panchayats are less than 40 sq km in area, half that size. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So chances are you&#x27;ll have to use the same reading for multiple panchayats and you won&#x27;t get any differentiation between them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2m air temperature tracks land surface temperatures and the two are &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;centaur.reading.ac.uk&#x2F;71902&#x2F;7&#x2F;Good_et_al-2017-Journal_of_Geophysical_Research__Atmospheres.pdf&quot;&gt;closely related&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, using surface temperature as a proxy indicator is acceptable, even if it isn&#x27;t a perfect substitute. It will allow us to compare one panchayat to another, and give us a rough idea of how hot or not people feel at different times of the day.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-really-a-climate-change-story&quot;&gt;Not really a climate change story&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we&#x27;re aren&#x27;t talking about changes on a global scale or tracking the increase in temperatures from pre-industrial levels hundreds of years ago or some other period like 1951-1980.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;09_usual_climate_change_story_pic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Typical image accompanying a climate change story&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;Typical image that accompanies climate change stories. Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;data.giss.nasa.gov&#x2F;gistemp&#x2F;maps&#x2F;index_v4.html&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more about increases in surface temperature that are a result of recent human interventions like building homes, shops, urbanisation in general.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For sure, climate change would&#x27;ve contributed in some part to the rise in temperatures, but it would be difficult for me at my skill level to quantify the exact contribution.) &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we won&#x27;t pay attention to effects like rise in sea levels, coastal erosion or erraticness in rainfall patterns. This is more about the impact on plain day-to-day livability, how high temperatures affect the movement of people during the day, their studies, their work etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;there-will-be-data-missing&quot;&gt;There will be data missing&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing with satellite data is that you only get observations when the sky is free of clouds. So because we&#x27;re dealing with Kerala, a state that has monsoon weather from June to November, six months in a row, there&#x27;s likely to be large gaps in the temperature data during that period. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&#x27;m ok with that because I&#x27;m thinking the rainy weather will be affecting all areas equally. Maybe some areas more than others on particular days, but that over a long enough period like five years, it all averages out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus the heating up of rural Kerala isn&#x27;t that evident to people during the monsoon months. It&#x27;s during the &#x27;fair weather&#x27; months of December to May that these hellish temperatures come into play. So even if less data is available for more-cloudier months, that is fine as our look into the discomfort people feel isn&#x27;t affected.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the interest of transparency, people should understand that the temperature estimates we&#x27;ve calculated here are not based on data for all days, but data for all days &lt;em&gt;it&#x27;s available&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-against-development&quot;&gt;Not against development&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now a rise in land surface temperature is an outcome of urbanisation, an increase in man-made structures etc., which is considered development by many. So if this development leads to jobs, a rise in incomes or new homes, isn&#x27;t that a good thing? &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I don&#x27;t have a problem with people trying to create a better situation for themselves and their families. I&#x27;m not against new construction, all I&#x27;m saying is that the heating up of rural Kerala is a result of everything that&#x27;s going on. And that authorities need to do more to counter this rise in temperatures by promoting use of white cement on roofs, rooftop gardens etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;points-of-interest-for-peers-in-indian-data-journalism&quot;&gt;Points of interest for peers in Indian data journalism&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess one thing that&#x27;s kind of innovative with this story is the extensive use of Microsoft&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;planetarycomputer.microsoft.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Planetary Computer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. One of the problems with using geospatial data is how big the files are sometimes, so your computer&#x27;s memory and processing limits can get in the way. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using services like Planetary Computer can help avoid that by offloading work to remote servers that are more powerful and have instant access to data. An alternative to Planetary Computer is Google Earth Engine, think I&#x27;ve seen Pulaha Roy from &lt;em&gt;Down to Earth&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; use it in his work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;kerala-panchayat-temp&#x2F;IMAGES&#x2F;10_planetary_computer_screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Planetary Computer homepage&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;Screenshot of Planetary Computer homepage&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I&#x27;ve worked hard at doing is to make the results in this story completely reproducible. The code is all there in a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;hottest-panchayats-kerala&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;code_final.ipynb&quot;&gt;jupyter notebook&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on Github, and it can be run cell by cell to get the original results. Whenever I&#x27;ve worked with geospatial data in the past, it&#x27;s usually been in graphical tools like QGIS, and it&#x27;s hard for others to replicate its results. There are no such issues here with the workflow fully in code.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve also tried to focus less on finding universal patterns or making generalisable claims. For example, when I looked at the hottest panchayats above or the ones that have heated up most, I didn&#x27;t try to come up with factors common to these panchayats that would explain  their situation. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I didn&#x27;t describe the rise in temperatures over southern Kerala as possibly an effect of their less urbanised starting point, because of which any growth leads to a marked rise in surface temperatures. I do make a point about the geographical location of these panchayats (ones in central Kerala hottest etc.) but that&#x27;s about it. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead I focused on individual panchayats (Vadakarapathy and Vijayapuram) and tried to see what data could tell us about them. A lot of journalism is actually just that, focusing on specific cases and I&#x27;d forgotten about this aspect of the profession.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I was reminded of it by a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;peabee.substack.com&#x2F;p&#x2F;17-one-kitchen-hundreds-of-internet&quot;&gt;2022 story&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from techie Prashant Baid that hyper-focused on one Bangalore cloud kitchen and exposed its shady practices with the help of data. I&#x27;m going to make a conscious effort to do similar investigative work that isn&#x27;t about making grand claims.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;suggestions-feedback&quot;&gt;Suggestions, feedback&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All code for my story is available in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;hottest-panchayats-kerala&quot;&gt;github repo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are things here I should be doing differently, do let me know! Contact me at mail@shijith.com or at this Twitter handle &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;shijith&quot;&gt;@shijith&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>What&#x27;s the best streaming service in India for western music?</title>
        <published>2022-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2022-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://shijith.com/blog/music-streaming-india/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://shijith.com/blog/music-streaming-india/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most streaming services in India offer western music, and I wanted to see how much access they give to critically-acclaimed albums from the past and present. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used features like &#x27;Best Albums Ever&#x27;, &#x27;Best albums of 2021&#x27; and so on from top music publications and websites to come up with a list of albums in each genre (Rock, EDM etc.) these services should have.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Services were rated out of 10 in each genre, with the rating corresponding to what percent of the album list they have in their library. To no surprise, Apple or Spotify came first in most lists.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the overall rating that looks at performance across all genres, the top four spots were taken by global services — Spotify (9.3&#x2F;10), Apple Music (9.3), YouTube Music (8.9) and Amazon Music (8.5). Of services based in India, only JioSaavn (8.1) came anywhere close.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, how well a service does depends on the deals it has in place with groups like Universal Music that control the landscape. An analysis of the albums available on each service and their copyright info shows that Spotify and Apple Music were able to strike deals with a wide variety of groups, resulting in their superior ratings. Other services, especially Indian ones, will have to put similar deals in place to serve listeners better.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to figure out how well various music services in India cater to people who listen to western music. For example, if you&#x27;re a discering fan of metal, how happy should you be with Apple, JioSaavn etc.? Does the service offer the best albums from the past few years? If some music critics got together and compiled the best 100 metal albums of all time, how many of them would a service have?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;kovid-rathee-PHGKkKf9K3I-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An Indian bass guitarist at a concert.&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;An Indian bass guitarist at a concert. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;unsplash.com&#x2F;photos&#x2F;PHGKkKf9K3I&quot;&gt;Kovid Rathee&#x2F;Unsplash&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I&#x27;m not really looking at the size of a service&#x27;s library, but how well they cover music at the &#x27;top end&#x27;. So not which service best covers each genre, but which service covers the best of each genre. In the marketing and promotional language for many of these services, they talk about how many millions of songs are there in their library, I won&#x27;t be using that metric. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also won&#x27;t be a holistic comparison of these services where we get into factors like streaming quality, mobile app features or subscription costs. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This analysis allows us to see what holes there are in the libraries of these music services, and also helps quantify in concrete terms the difference in coverage between them. Listeners can hopefully use this post to make more informed decisions about which subscription to go for.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-i-went-about-it&quot;&gt;How I went about it&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, I chose 10 genres (Pop, Rock, Jazz etc.) to represent the diversity of western music. Could&#x27;ve gone for more, I&#x27;ve excluded country and folk music for example, but I think the 10 genres selected cover most of what the West has to offer. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I researched which books, magazines or websites are respected in each genre, and what albums they&#x27;ve deemed as the best of all time (the &#x27;canon&#x27;) or the best of recent times. For example, for EDM (electronic dance music), the canon was taken from a list of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mixmag.net&#x2F;feature&#x2F;the-50-most-influential-dance-music-albums-of-all-time&quot;&gt;most influential albums&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by dance music publication Mixmag. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;mixmag_screenshot.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Mixmag.com screenshot.&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best contemporary albums were taken from annual &#x27;Best Albums of 20XX&#x27; lists from dance publication Resident Advisor for the last 10 years. This gave me a list of 50 albums for the canon and 267 albums for the contemporary category.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These albums were searched for programatically, and sometimes manually, on each of these services. I tallied how many each service had, and after weighting the canon and contemporary equally, a rating for each service was given out of 10. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spotify, for example, had 46&#x2F;50 albums in the canon list, and 236&#x2F;267 in contemporary. That translates to 4.6&#x2F;5 points for canon and 4.4&#x2F;5 for contemporary, for a total rating of 9&#x2F;10 for EDM.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A more technical write-up on how I implemented everything, and all the code is available at the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;music-streaming-india&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some genre afficionados could question why one list was chosen and not another. Going for a specific list is actually down to more mundane factors like availability online or how it&#x27;s been compiled. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I&#x27;ve used the magazine &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.downbeat.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Downbeat&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to get lists of the best contemporary blues albums for each year. By some accounts, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;livingblues.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Living Blues&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; magazine is the more respected blues publication, but their annual list isn&#x27;t compiled by critics but is based on radio airplay, so I decided not to use it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I accept that these lists are subjective. Ideally, a streaming service should be able to accommodate any best albums list that critics come up with. But taking any one list should good enough as a starting point.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some might also question the use of albums, instead of individual songs, to compare streaming services. That people &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.digitalmusicnews.com&#x2F;2019&#x2F;10&#x2F;04&#x2F;are-albums-dying&#x2F;&quot;&gt;don&#x27;t really listen to whole albums&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; anymore, that they don&#x27;t consume their music that way. But I felt that checking for, say, 100 whole albums would be a sterner test for these services than checking for 100 individual songs, so I went with albums.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;overall-ratings&quot;&gt;Overall ratings&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we combine the ratings for different genres, Spotify and Apple Music are tied for top spot with a rating of 9.3&#x2F;10. YouTube Music comes in 3rd with an overall rating of 8.9 and Amazon Music 4th with 8.5. These four global services taking the top spots isn&#x27;t that suprising considering the resources they have available to make deals with music groups of all sizes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;overall_ratings_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Overall Ratings&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I started the research, my gut feeling was that music coverage is pretty much a &#x27;solved&#x27; problem in India. That if you&#x27;re into western music, you can pretty much choose any service and all your musical needs would be met. That services now differentiate themselves on other factors like stream bitrates or plan pricing, and that you choose between services based on those criteria.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guessed wrong, because outside of Spotify and Apple, there are still significant gaps when it comes to music coverage. If you listen primarily to western music and want to subscribe to a streaming service, it&#x27;s hard to recommend anything other than Spotify or Apple.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pop&quot;&gt;Pop&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: Slant &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.slantmagazine.com&#x2F;music&#x2F;vital-pop-50-essential-pop-albums&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&#x27;50 Essential Pop Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: AllMusic &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.allmusic.com&#x2F;year-in-review&#x2F;2021&#x2F;favorite-pop&quot;&gt;&#x27;Favorite Pop Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; annual list 2012-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting off with Pop—where your Madonnas, Lady Gagas and Taylor Swifts of the world reside—5 of the 8 services do well here with ratings over 9.0, with Apple Music topping at 9.8.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;pop_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Pop Ratings&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spotify lost 0.1 points from its pop rating as it didn&#x27;t have Joni Mitchell&#x27;s 1974 album &#x27;Court and Spark&#x27;, seen as part of the canon by Slant&#x27;s list. This is a result of the &#x27;70s icon &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.rollingstone.com&#x2F;music&#x2F;music-news&#x2F;joni-mitchell-spotify-catalog-1292397&#x2F;&quot;&gt;pulling her music&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from the service to protest against the spread of covid misinformation by Joe Rogan&#x27;s podcast on Spotify.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;edm&quot;&gt;EDM&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: Mixmag &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mixmag.net&#x2F;feature&#x2F;the-50-most-influential-dance-music-albums-of-all-time&quot;&gt;&#x27;50 Most Influential Dance Music Albums Of All Time&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: Resident Advisor &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ra.co&#x2F;features&#x2F;3950&quot;&gt;&#x27;Best Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; annual lists 2012-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After hip-hop, EDM I guess has had the most influence on the sound of today&#x27;s pop music. But for such an influential genre, it doesn&#x27;t really get much coverage, with only two services Spotify and Apple getting 9 or more.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;edm_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;EDM Ratings&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two albums from the EDM canon — &#x27;Alcachofa&#x27; by Ricardo Villalobos and &#x27;Just an Example&#x27; by	Shy FX — aren&#x27;t there on any service in India.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;rock&quot;&gt;Rock&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: Classic Rock &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;pub37.bravenet.com&#x2F;forum&#x2F;static&#x2F;show.php?usernum=3172289350&amp;amp;frmid=10&amp;amp;msgid=603995&quot;&gt;&#x27;100 Greatest Rock Albums Ever&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: AllMusic &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.allmusic.com&#x2F;year-in-review&#x2F;2021&#x2F;favorite-rock&quot;&gt;&#x27;Favorite Rock Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; annual lists 2012-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rock may not matter as much as it used to, but it&#x27;s well served as a genre with four services getting ratings over 9 for the genre. There are some holes though in YouTube Music&#x27;s coverage with no &#x27;Hotel California&#x27; album by the Eagles or no &#x27;Electric Ladyland&#x27; by Jimi Hendrix.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neil Young&#x27;s 2012 album &#x27;Psychedelic Pill&#x27; isn&#x27;t on Spotify, along with several of his older albums. Like Joni Mitchell, he too had his albums &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.billboard.com&#x2F;business&#x2F;streaming&#x2F;spotify-removes-neil-young-music-joe-rogan-vaccines-1235023517&#x2F;&quot;&gt;removed from Spotify&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to protest against covid misinformation on the platform.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;rock_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Rock Ratings&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;metal&quot;&gt;Metal&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: Rolling Stone &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.rollingstone.com&#x2F;music&#x2F;music-lists&#x2F;the-100-greatest-metal-albums-of-all-time-113614&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&#x27;100 Greatest Metal Albums Of All Time&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: Metal Hammer &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.facebook.com&#x2F;groups&#x2F;195830297121202&#x2F;posts&#x2F;4779431462094373&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&#x27;Top Metal Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; annual lists 2012-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll be honest, I had no idea people were into metal in India. It&#x27;s only when I started hanging out in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;india&#x2F;comments&#x2F;uwkmf1&#x2F;metalheads_of_rindia_could_you_suggest_your&#x2F;&quot;&gt;reddit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; did I realise how much of a following it&#x27;s got here. If we take the genre as a whole, the services cover it well with 5 of them getting ratings over 9. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;metal_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;XXX Metal RATINGS XXX&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of availability, there&#x27;s an album &#x27;Jerusalem&#x27; by the band Sleep and an album &#x27;Torture Garden&#x27; by Naked City that aren&#x27;t there on any of the services in India. I&#x27;m not into metal myself, so don&#x27;t know how big of a deal that is. But everything else seen as canon by the Rolling Stone list is available either on Apple or Spotify.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;hip-hop&quot;&gt;Hip-Hop&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: HipHopGoldenAge.com &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hiphopgoldenage.com&#x2F;list&#x2F;the-best-250-hip-hop-albums-of-all-time&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&#x27;Best 250 Hip-Hop Albums of All Time&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: HotNewHipHop.com &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.hotnewhiphop.com&#x2F;top-30-hottest-hip-hop-albums-of-2021-news.143625.html&quot;&gt;&#x27;Hottest Hip-Hop Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; annual lists 2012-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very influential, and well served by most of the music services in India, with 5 services scoring over 9. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;hip_hop_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Hip-Hop Ratings&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missing from all services (except curiously JioSaavn) is Snoop Dogg&#x27;s breakthrough album &#x27;Doggystyle&#x27; and another &#x27;90s album &#x27;Chronic&#x27; by Dr Dre. Seems the albums were pulled because the artists &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hypebeast.com&#x2F;2022&#x2F;4&#x2F;snoop-dogg-plans-to-start-own-death-row-streaming-platform-app&quot;&gt;were unhappy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with how much they were being paid from streaming. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Jay-Z&#x27;s biggest albums &#x27;The Blueprint&#x27; isn&#x27;t on YouTube Music, not sure why. Seems it was pulled from all services a few years ago to become exclusive to Jay Z&#x27;s own music service Tidal. It &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.complex.com&#x2F;music&#x2F;2019&#x2F;05&#x2F;jay-z-blueprint-albums-are-back-on-apple-music&quot;&gt;came back later&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to all services, don&#x27;t see it on YouTube Music though.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;r-b&quot;&gt;R&amp;amp;B&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: BlackExcellence.com &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.blackexcellence.com&#x2F;best-rb-albums-of-all-time-2&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&#x27;40 Best R&amp;amp;B Albums Of All Time&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: ThisisRnB.com &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;thisisrnb.com&#x2F;2016&#x2F;12&#x2F;thisisrnb-presents-the-20-best-rb-albums-of-2016&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&#x27;Best R&amp;amp;B Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; annual lists 2012-2016, RatedRnB.com &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ratedrnb.com&#x2F;2021&#x2F;12&#x2F;the-30-best-rnb-albums-of-2021-staff-picks&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&#x27;Best R&amp;amp;B Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; annual lists 2017-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artists representing this genre are Beyonce, Mariah Carey and John Legend. Most services do well in the R&amp;amp;B genre, with 5 of them scoring over 9. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;rnb_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;R&amp;amp;B Ratings XXX&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some past acts whose albums are missing are Boyz II Men (&#x27;90s album II missing from YouTube Music) and Alicia Keys (2016 album &#x27;Here&#x27; isn&#x27;t on Amazon Music).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;jazz&quot;&gt;Jazz&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;people.ucalgary.ca&#x2F;~ghfick&#x2F;jazz.html&quot;&gt;Albums awarded &#x27;crowns&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by Penguin Guide to Jazz recordings&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: Downbeat magazine Critics Poll &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.downbeat.com&#x2F;digitaledition&#x2F;2021&#x2F;DB21_08&#x2F;DB21_08.pdf&quot;&gt;&#x27;Best Jazz Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; 2012-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jazz is one of only two genres in which no service has a rating over 9 (the other being World Music). It&#x27;s also the genre that Apple and Spotify do most poorly in. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;jazz_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Jazz Ratings&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The low ratings are also a result of how strict I&#x27;ve needed to be. Take for example, the compilation album &#x27;Major Works of John Coltrane&#x27; which isn&#x27;t available on any service in India. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the tracks from that album will be there in other compilations available on each service. So you could technically recreate the experience of listening to the album by making a playlist that cuts and pastes those tracks together. That will feel like you&#x27;re listening to the album, but it&#x27;ll still have to be marked as unavailable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have made exceptions though. If there&#x27;s a compilation by another name that has all the tracks of the album and there&#x27;s not too many extra pieces to sit through, I&#x27;ve accepted that as a substitute.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another artist whose collected works isn&#x27;t available on Spotify or Apple is Charlie Parker and his &#x27;Complete Savoy &amp;amp; Dial Studio Recordings&#x27;. It is available on Amazon and Youtube Music though. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;blues&quot;&gt;Blues&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;people.ucalgary.ca&#x2F;~ghfick&#x2F;blues.html&quot;&gt;Albums awarded &#x27;crowns&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by Penguin Guide to Blues Recordings&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: Downbeat magazine Critics Poll &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.downbeat.com&#x2F;digitaledition&#x2F;2021&#x2F;DB21_08&#x2F;DB21_08.pdf&quot;&gt;&#x27;Best Blues Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; 2012-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, the major services — Spotify, Apple, YouTube, Amazon — all do better in covering Blues than Jazz. You think it would be the opposite given how Blues and Blues artists aren&#x27;t as well-known. Spotify even manages to score a 9 here.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;blues_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Blues Ratings&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s one collected work SRV by Stevie Ray Vaughan that&#x27;s not available on any service. But I don&#x27;t really listen to the Blues, so I&#x27;m not sure how big an omission that is.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;western-classical&quot;&gt;Western Classical&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: Gramophone Classical Music Guide &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;archive.org&#x2F;details&#x2F;gramophoneclassi0000unse_x9k8&#x2F;page&#x2F;n17&#x2F;mode&#x2F;2up&quot;&gt;&#x27;100 Great Recordings&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: Gramophone Awards &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;reader.exacteditions.com&#x2F;issues&#x2F;96463&#x2F;spread&#x2F;19&quot;&gt;&#x27;Contemporary&#x27; category nominees&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; 2012-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only Apple and Spotify do well here with ratings over 9. Was surprised to see other global services like YouTube Music and Amazon doing poorly in this, both had ratings around 7.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;western_classical_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Western Classical Ratings&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a result of how strict I&#x27;ve had to be when it comes to accepting albums as substitutes. The thing with western classical is that there can be a 100 different performances or interpretations of the same work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if we take the opera &#x27;Fidelio&#x27; composed by Beethoven, there&#x27;s one recording of a performance in 1961 at the Royal Opera House in London conducted by Otto Klemperer. Another recording is of the performance in 1962 at Kingsway Hall in London, also conducted by Klemperer. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gramophone guide recommends the 1961 version, so even if the 1962 version is available on a service, it doesn&#x27;t count. We may not be privy to the logic why the guide went for one over the other, but we assume that there are good reasons, and so we stick to its choices and try not to deviate from them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;world-music&quot;&gt;World Music&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists used&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Canon: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;osmelhoresdiscos.blogspot.com&#x2F;2010&#x2F;08&#x2F;rough-guide-to-world-100-essential-cds.html&quot;&gt;Rough Guide to World Music: 100 Essential CDs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
— Contemporary: Songlines &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.songlines.co.uk&#x2F;news&#x2F;the-10-best-albums-of-2021&quot;&gt;&#x27;Best Albums&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; annual lists 2012-2021&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess one could question if a category called &#x27;World Music&#x27; should be here. A diverse collection of genres from around the globe, this isn&#x27;t actually music from the West. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But given how &#x27;World Music&#x27; is a beneficiary of western musical tastes, how it&#x27;s an important tool used by westerners to organise the musical diversity around them, it felt important to include. (In fact, a more honest title for this blog post is not &amp;quot;What&#x27;s the best streaming service in India for western music?&amp;quot;, but &amp;quot;Which streaming service in India best caters to western musical taste?&amp;quot;)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;world_music_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;World Music Ratings&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Jazz, world music is the only other genre where no service has a rating over 9. The closest that comes to it is Spotify with 8.8. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;rolling-stone-500-nme-500&quot;&gt;Rolling Stone 500 &amp;amp; NME 500&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#x27;t part of the overall rating, but is just something I was curious about. The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.rollingstone.com&#x2F;music&#x2F;music-lists&#x2F;best-albums-of-all-time-1062063&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Rolling Stone 500&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is the premier list of &#x27;best albums&#x27; and it&#x27;s been around since 2003. The latest version was done in 2020, and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.rollingstone.com&#x2F;music&#x2F;music-news&#x2F;voters-500-greatest-albums-list-1062225&#x2F;&quot;&gt;hundreds&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of critics were involved in compiling it. I wanted to see how the various services did when it came to covering the latest RS 500. 5 of the services did well with over 400 of the 500 albums on the list.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;rolling_stone_500_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Rolling Stone 500 Count&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highest-ranking album on the RS 500 that&#x27;s not on any service in India is 37th-ranked &#x27;The Chronic&#x27; by Dr. Dre. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m a bit of an anglophile, so I also wanted to see how the services would do with a version of the RS 500 that&#x27;s more UK-oriented. I found &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.rocklistmusic.co.uk&#x2F;nme_500_greatest_albums_2013.htm&quot;&gt;&#x27;The 500 Greatest Albums of All Time&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; list put out by the British publication NME in 2013, and checked how the services did against that list. All the major services had over 400 of the 500 albums available.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;nme_500_blog.webp&quot; alt=&quot;NME 500 Count&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-all-comes-down-to-label-agreements&quot;&gt;It all comes down to label agreements&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albums missing from a streaming service, or the service doing poorly in a genre is a result of the deals streaming services have done—or not done—with major labels and other music groups. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &#x27;Big Three&#x27; majors are Universal Music Group, Sony Music Group and Warner Music Group, and signing deals with these three gives a service access to most music under the sun. Another group that services need to deal with to round out their offerings is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;merlinnetwork.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Merlin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a body that acts on behalf of many independent labels  operating outside the majors.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, what we&#x27;re actually looking at in this post is the extent of these legal relationships with global music groups, and the &#x27;mapping&#x27; from that to different genres and how they&#x27;re covered. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more music groups a streaming service has deals with, and the more extensive the nature of those deals, the better a service&#x27;s coverage is across genres.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Services don&#x27;t acquire rights or licenses for single albums, but whole libraries. If an album is part of the catalogue offered under the agreement, the service gets access to it, otherwise they don&#x27;t.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The webpage for every album on the service website mentions who holds the copyrights. By collecting that info for the over 3,000 albums in our dataset, and by seeing which label is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;data&#x2F;label_groups.py&quot;&gt;under which group&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, we are able to figure out which albums come under what deals for over 90% of the dataset. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you look at the Apple Music page for Aretha Franklin&#x27;s album &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;music.apple.com&#x2F;in&#x2F;album&#x2F;amazing-grace-live-at-new-temple-missionary-baptist&#x2F;1628093959&quot;&gt;&#x27;Amazing Grace&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, the copyright info given is &#x27;℗ 2022 Atlantic Recording Corporation&#x27;. Atlantic record label comes under Warner Music, so this album should come as part of any deal done with Warner.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(There&#x27;s an additional level of complexity in that there are &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;completemusicupdate.com&#x2F;article&#x2F;trends-music-licensing-explained-at-last&#x2F;&quot;&gt;different copyrights&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for a song and for the &lt;em&gt;recording&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of a song. And a service has to have deals in place with the different copyright holders if it wants to offer a song. Most services only display the info for the latter correctly, the &#x27;phonographic&#x27; copyright ℗, so we&#x27;ll focus on that. One problem is &#x27;composition&#x27; copyrights © to a song could sometimes be with a publishing company under a different music group. But when a streaming service makes a deal with a music major, the deal &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.musicbusinessworldwide.com&#x2F;warner-sues-spotify-in-india-as-licensing-negotiations-hit-major-speed-bump&#x2F;&quot;&gt;usually involves&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; the publishing company under it, so making deals with all majors should cover all eventualities.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The table below is an attempt to see how much each music group contributes to the albums in my dataset. Not in absolute numbers, but in terms of the overall rating. Our rating is out of 10, and albums from the Univeral Music Group (including labels like Capitol, Geffen and Decca) are responsible for 2.34 points in our 10 point rating, so its contribution is 23.4%. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;label_tieup.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Music group deals and services&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s a separate entry &#x27;Universal (Indie)&#x27; which covers independent labels like Concord whose work is distributed by Universal or its distribution arms like Ingrooves. Don&#x27;t know if I need this separate category, I&#x27;m assuming that music services would need to make separate deals with Universal to cover its own labels, and to cover independent labels distributed by it, and so the latter should be treated differently. Don&#x27;t know if that&#x27;s the case in reality, but it felt important to maintain this logical distinction, so I&#x27;ve kept things as is.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the albums that aren&#x27;t available on a service and their copyright info, we can reasonably speculate about the music groups streaming services don&#x27;t have deals with.  Gaana has poor coverage of albums from Universal, meaning the Indian service may not have an agreement with them, and so it loses upto 2.3 of 10 points in the overall rating.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are my guesses about deals that aren&#x27;t in place for each service:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spotify&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — As far as I can make out, they seem to have deals with most of the groups. A record label Ilian Tape &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;crackmagazine.net&#x2F;2022&#x2F;01&#x2F;ilian-tape-removes-entire-back-catalogue-from-spotify-says-its-time-for-a-change&#x2F;&quot;&gt;removed its catalogue&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from Spotify to protest against what they see as poor payments for streaming. As a result, 4 EDM albums in the dataset (3 of them from the act Skee Mask) are missing, affecting Spotify&#x27;s EDM rating.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple Music&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Seems to have deals with most groups&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Music&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — The service in India doesn&#x27;t have albums from Chrysalis Records, Domino Recording, Merge Records, Sub Pop and Warp Records. This includes albums from acts like Aphex Twin, My Bloody Valentine and Arctic Monkeys. Amazon&#x27;s Rock and EDM coverage are especially affected by this. These record labels are members of Merlin, but the work of other Merlin members are available on Amazon, so not sure what&#x27;s going on here.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YouTube Music&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Albums copyrighted to ECM records are missing from the service in India, affecting its jazz and western classical coverage. A total of 13 jazz and 5 western classical albums from ECM are unavailable. It isn&#x27;t clear, but ECM is either &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.universalmusic.com&#x2F;label&#x2F;verve-label-group&#x2F;#ecm&quot;&gt;a part&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of the Universal Music Group or an independent label whose work is distributed by Universal. So if YouTube Music has a deal with Universal, not sure why ECM Records albums aren&#x27;t part of that deal. Many classical music albums copyrighted to Decca Records of Universal are also missing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JioSaavn&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — There&#x27;s one prominent music company Beggars Group whose albums are missing from JioSaavn. They aren&#x27;t associated with any of the majors and are part of Merlin, who actually &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;merlinnetwork.org&#x2F;merlin-and-jiosaavn-sign-enhanced-global-music-licensing-partnership&#x2F;&quot;&gt;have a deal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with JioSaavn, but I guess Beggars isn&#x27;t part of it. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beggars Group record labels include Matador, Rough Trade and XL Recordings, and artists whose work is missing because of this include Radiohead, EDM act XX and singer Adele. So JioSaavn has Adele&#x27;s album &#x27;30&#x27; but not her older album &#x27;21&#x27;. In total, 14 EDM and 15 Rock albums are missing because of this. From news reports, it seems Beggars prefers to have &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;musically.com&#x2F;2018&#x2F;04&#x2F;05&#x2F;beggars-group-china-real-issue-exclusivity&#x2F;&quot;&gt;their own deals&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with music services in China. So maybe when it comes to larger economies like China and India, Beggars prefers to do deals outside of Merlin to get a bigger cut, and for some reason there isn&#x27;t a deal with JioSaavn.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaana&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Pretty much all albums associated with Universal Music are missing from the service, which probably means Gaana doesn&#x27;t have a deal with them. Albums from The Beatles, Nirvana and Kanye West are missing as a result. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now when I started my research a few months back, I think these albums were there then, and them not being there now means the deal has lapsed and not been renewed. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reuters.com&#x2F;technology&#x2F;exclusive-fighting-survive-tencent-backed-indian-music-app-gaana-turns-2022-09-09&#x2F;&quot;&gt;A report came out&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; a few days ago about money being tight at Gaana. Even if I&#x27;m mistaken about all this, the fact remains these albums aren&#x27;t there now, and this absence affects Gaana in all genres. Its overall rating would jump from a lowly 3.0 to 5.3 if it had a deal with Universal.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hungama &amp;amp; Wynk&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — From what I can tell, neither of them have a deal with Merlin. If they did, their coverage would improve across genres, and the overall rating would go up atleast 1.5 points for both services.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;caveats-doubts&quot;&gt;Caveats, doubts&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What more I could&#x27;ve done, and things to keep in mind when going through the findings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Resso&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — One service that should&#x27;ve been part of the comparison is Chinese music app Resso. Had no idea this &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;entrackr.com&#x2F;2020&#x2F;03&#x2F;bytedance-resso-launches-in-india&#x2F;&quot;&gt;was around&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, till I was too far along into my research. But even if I had known about it, I may not have included it because it doesn&#x27;t have a website interface, and is available only as a desktop or mobile app. Being able to query various services through their websites made my job a lot easier, and, unfortunately, extracting information from mobile apps isn&#x27;t in my toolbox yet :( &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;resso_homepage.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Resso homepage&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YouTube excluded&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — One service that I&#x27;ve intentionally left out is YouTube itself. The main YouTube isn&#x27;t a music streaming service, but I&#x27;m pretty sure most people in India listen to or &#x27;watch&#x27; their music this way. From official videos to pirated ones to bootleg versions, everything&#x27;s on here. If this was part of the ratings — and putting questions of legality aside — I&#x27;m pretty sure YouTube would be on top with a 10&#x2F;10 score. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just felt I should acknowledge how streaming services aren&#x27;t the only options available to users when it comes to getting music. And that the most popular option isn&#x27;t here because it&#x27;s technically a video-sharing platform.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;False positives and negatives&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — False positives here are albums the code is telling me are there, but aren&#x27;t really because they&#x27;re &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;.&#x2F;#ghost&quot;&gt;&#x27;ghost&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; albums or albums by a tribute band that&#x27;s mistaken for the real thing and so on. I&#x27;ve checked most of the results manually, maybe a few might slip through, but on the whole false positives shouldn&#x27;t be a problem. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;False negatives are albums that are there in a streaming service&#x27;s library, but my code couldn&#x27;t find them. I&#x27;m trusting my code to be good enough that it gets most of the albums that are available, so even if I do miss a few of them, the service&#x27;s rating won&#x27;t be affected by much in most cases. One way to avoid false negatives is to search for albums manually, but I felt that would defeat one of the goals here which is to do everything programatically as much as possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The focus on expert instead of popular tastes&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Another way these ratings could&#x27;ve been constructed is by paying attention to the taste of the masses, as opposed to critics. For determining the canon, I could&#x27;ve looked at what the top 100 best-selling albums of all time are in each genre and checked how many of those 100 each service has. It&#x27;s just that I felt it important to apply some level of expert judgement since we are talking about the &#x27;best&#x27; albums, not &#x27;best-selling&#x27; albums. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is the danger that a critic could choose an album that fans don&#x27;t listen to much. So if it&#x27;s in the long tail in terms of popularity, should a service be penalised for not having it? Those albums being unavailable might not affect how a listener enjoys a service as long as they provide everything on the popular end of the spectrum.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rethink 50% weightage for canon&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — The way I&#x27;ve constructed the ratings, 50% weight is given to albums that critics consider the &#x27;canon&#x27;, the best albums of all time in a genre. But I have the feeling for listeners of particular genres, the canon might not matter as much. Take pop music, where more attention is given by listeners to more recent albums. Here I think it&#x27;s unlikely that someone who listens to 20-year-old pop singer Billie Eilish would consider it equally important to listen to the Beatles, an act whose main albums came out 5 decades ago. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While for some other genres like western classical or jazz, I think listeners give more attention to the canon than recent works. Without more of an idea of how people listen, I think the 50-50 split between the canon and more recent work is a neutral and acceptable split. But yes, a case could be made for the split to vary according to the genre to reflect the importance listeners give different time periods, and so make these ratings more useful for them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Categories too broad?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Another issue that could affect the utility of this analysis to listeners is that the categorisation might be too broad for some. For example, I&#x27;ve used metal as a genre, but listener tastes might be more sophisticated in that they listen to sub-genres like death metal or black metal or shoegaze metal, and may not necessarily identify with the larger metal genre. In fact, it might even be important for them to identify &lt;em&gt;against&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; such broad tastes. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So telling someone that some service has this rating for metal wouldn&#x27;t really matter to them, because what really matters to them is how services do in the particular niche of metal they follow. One way to solve for this would&#x27;ve been to present this analysis in an interactive format, and allow users to drill down into the specific sub-genre they follow, and construct a customised rating that suits them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-notes&quot;&gt;Side notes&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random thoughts and observations that don&#x27;t fit elsewhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;ghost&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem of &#x27;ghost&#x27; albums&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — This is something I find really annoying about the search results on some services. &#x27;Ghost&#x27; albums are albums that you search for on a service, you get a result for it, and then you click on it, only to find that most of the tracks aren&#x27;t available. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a video of what happens when I search for the album &#x27;Hotel California&#x27; by The Eagles on YouTube Music. The album shows up in the results, but when I click on individual tracks, they&#x27;re all greyed out and won&#x27;t play.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay loop&gt;&lt;source src=&quot;output.webm&quot; type=&quot;video&#x2F;webm&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;video&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other services like Hungama and Wynk are guilty of this too, and it&#x27;s really frustrating for the end-user. I know these are essentially placeholder entries for albums that a service may not have the rights for at the moment, and could in the future. But till they do, I feel those albums shouldn&#x27;t show up in search results. Makes for a bad user experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple and Spotify well-integrated already&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Another reason why someone should go only for Apple or Spotify is that they are integrated into the music ecosystem in a way few other services are. For example, if I&#x27;m listening to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.bbc.co.uk&#x2F;sounds&#x2F;brand&#x2F;m0010r87&quot;&gt;Late in the Day&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; mix on BBC Sounds, I like a song and want to bookmark it in some way, there are only two services that BBC Sounds is linked to — Apple Music and Spotify. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or say I&#x27;m reading Pitchfork&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pitchfork.com&#x2F;features&#x2F;lists-and-guides&#x2F;best-songs-2021&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&#x27;100 Best Songs of 2021&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; feature and I want to listen to all the songs, the tracks will have been put up on playlists, but only on Spotify and Apple Music. So because of how omnipresent these two services are, you gravitate towards them anyway. Using other services involves just too much &#x27;friction&#x27;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Streaming may not fit some lifestyles&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — However well a music service might cover a genre like jazz or western classical, I have a feeling it wouldn&#x27;t affect the choices of enthusiasts, and convince them to subscribe to these services. Because listeners of these genres may be at such income levels that importing CDs or even vinyl to hear music isn&#x27;t really an issue for them, so they wouldn&#x27;t bother with Spotify etc. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For such people, having those albums in a physical form and being able to display them is important to demonstrate their tastes to others, as an outward expression of their identity. Also for classical music, there are more specialised streaming services like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.idagio.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Idagio&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that have a more extensive catalogue, so even if people do subscribe, it would be to services like this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;music-streaming-india&#x2F;idagio_homepage.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Idagio.com homepage&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;taking-things-forward&quot;&gt;Taking things forward&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve focused on western music here, but someone else could take this work forward by looking at the various music services and looking at how well they cover Indian music. The code&#x27;s all there in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;music-streaming-india&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, all you would need is a dataset of albums for each Indian language from the past and present that are critically acclaimed. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difficulty with doing something for Indian music is finding publications whose judgement you can trust. With the publications and websites I used here for my lists, there were multiple &#x27;signals&#x27;, including mentions in other publications, which made me confident about using them. The thing with Indian music is because there are multiple languages here, it&#x27;s difficult for outsiders to get a sense of which publication or website is reliable without using Google Translate to an annoying extent.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess one way you could do it while still sticking to English-language websites is to collect info on the National Film awards or State Film Awards for the last N years, look at the movies&#x2F;composers&#x2F;singers that get nominated, and use the lists of nominees to compile a dataset. Unfortunately, this will exclude the independent music scene outside movies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- ### Want to hire me?

I&#x27;ve been on a pandemic break, but with this project over, I&#x27;m ready to get back to full-time work. Have a look at the rest of [my website](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;). If you like what I&#x27;ve done and think I could be of value to your company, email me at [mail@shijith.com](mailto:mail@shijith.com) or message me on [LinkedIn](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.linkedin.com&#x2F;in&#x2F;shijith&#x2F;). --&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Which wikipedia pages in India are abused the most?</title>
        <published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://shijith.com/blog/wikipedia-page-abuse/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://shijith.com/blog/wikipedia-page-abuse/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post tries to find out which wikipedia pages on India are abused the most. And by abuse, I mean people editing wikipedia pages to twist the truth and present their own version of events. Abuse here also covers blatant vandalism like deleting whole sections from a page. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The level of abuse was determined by checking over 150,000 pages related to India on Wikipedia, going through their edit histories, and tallying how many users have had edits reverted. An edit being reverted is a sign that the edit was bad, or worse, malicious. So the number of users getting reverted on a page gives an idea of how much abuse a page is facing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2021 (or to be precise, the first 11 months of 2021), the page on the 2021 Tamil Nadu assembly elections was the page most abused with 215 users having their edits reverted this year. And if we look at pages outside politics, the page on the 2021 Bollywood movie &#x27;Radhe&#x27; was the most violated, with 324 users having their edits reverted. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post goes into how these conclusions were reached, and introduces a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;abuse_checker&quot;&gt;twitter account&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that tracks this abuse weekly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation-for-the-post&quot;&gt;Motivation for the post&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decided to do this analysis after reading an &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.onmanorama.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;kerala&#x2F;2021&#x2F;08&#x2F;15&#x2F;onam-wikipedia-page-edit-wars-right-wing-mobs.amp.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by Ronnie Kuriakose about the wikipedia page on Onam. It was being repeatedly changed to emphasise the festival&#x27;s Hindu aspects, and play down how Onam is celebrated  across religious communities in the state. Googling a little more about wikipedia abuse in India, I then came across a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;caravanmagazine.in&#x2F;media&#x2F;wikipedia-earned-ire-hindu-right&quot;&gt;story&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by Nishant Kauntia about how wikipedia pages related to current events were being altered. For example, the page on the Delhi riots of 2020 was being continually edited to misrepresent the role Hindu mobs played in attacking Muslims.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading these news stories, I wanted to see if I could keep track of these wikipedia attacks in a systematic way. So not wait for a reporter to get wind of these things happening on Wikipedia, and then tell me about it through an article. But build some tool that flags articles being subject to mass abuse, and does so on a periodic basis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool&#x27;s results can be seen on twitter at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;abuse_checker&quot;&gt;@abuse_checker&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which will tweet out two simple graphics every Monday morning. The first graphic names pages, political and non-political, that were abused the most the previous week. And the second graphic, the pages facing the biggest delta or increase in abuse compared to the week earlier. Here&#x27;s the graphics for this week:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;wikipedia-page-abuse&#x2F;past_1_week.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Most abused Indian pages on Wikipedia last week&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;wikipedia-page-abuse&#x2F;delta_from_last_week.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The Indian pages on Wikipedia facing biggest increase in abuse&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-tracking-abuse-could-be-important&quot;&gt;Why tracking abuse could be important&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is Wikipedia is very important to the online world. It&#x27;s one of the top results in any google search, and is also the source for infocards that appear next to google searches. It&#x27;s not an exaggeration to say that wikipedia is a foundational source of knowledge on the internet now. So getting to shape its pages in a certain way theoretically allows you to influence how others think about a topic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s a matter for academia whether influence works as uni-directional or one-way as this, or if this is an overstatement of wikipedia&#x27;s power, but there is no doubt that the people abusing the website believe it to be important in some way or the other, and that belief drives their need to alter its content.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;measuring-abuse&quot;&gt;Measuring abuse&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I&#x27;m measuring abuse is by counting the number of users who&#x27;ve had their edits reverted over a period. So what happens is every time a wikipedia user tries to do something malicious on a page and they&#x27;re found out, an editor tries to improve the edit first by rephrasing or correcting it. But if there&#x27;s too much that&#x27;s wrong about the offending edit, it&#x27;s then tagged as &#x27;reverted&#x27; and the page restored to the version that existed prior to the reverted edit. So if you add up the number of edits tagged &#x27;reverted&#x27;, you should get an idea of how much abuse a page is being subject to.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;wikipedia-page-abuse&#x2F;reverted_tag_screenshot.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a page&#x27;s edit history where an edit has been tagged reverted&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;Screenshot of a page&#x27;s edit history where an edit has been tagged reverted (circled in red)&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I try to do one better by not tallying up the number of reverted edits, but tallying up the number of users responsible for those edits. I wanted to avoid situations where a few users may be doing most of the malicious edits on a page. The number of unique users also gives a better idea of how widespread online discontent may be with a particular page.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now even edits that are done in good faith and without intending to twist the truth can fall short of wikipedia&#x27;s standards and get reverted. So the final figures will have a margin of error to them, but they should still be good enough to give a sense of which pages are the most abused.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for which pages were chosen for monitoring, over 150,000 articles assessed by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.m.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Wikipedia:WikiProject_India&quot;&gt;WikiProject India&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;—a group of wikipedia editors responsible for maintaining articles about India—were taken. A &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;wikipedia_abuse_checker&quot;&gt;python script&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; checks changes made to these pages every week and then tweets out graphics every Monday morning.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;most-abused-pages-of-2021&quot;&gt;Most abused pages of 2021&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look back at 2021 through the lens of wikipedia abuse, which pages have fallen victim the most?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I should make it clear these violations may have only been on the page for a few hours or days before someone caught it and reverted it. So this is more a record of failed attempts at abuse, rather than successful ones.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we just look at articles related to India politics, the page covering the 2021 Tamil Nadu Assembly elections saw the most abuse with 215 users reverted in 2021. Pages about elections that happened this year or are coming up in 2022 like the UP elections generally saw a lot of abuse.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;wikipedia-page-abuse&#x2F;2021_top_10.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Most abused Indian pages on Wikipedia in 2021&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One entry in the top 10 I didn&#x27;t know much about was Muhammad Iqbal. The national poet of Pakistan, he wrote the patriotic song &#x27;Saare Jahan Se Acha&#x27; that many Indians are familiar with, and he was also the first to present the two-nation theory of Muslims deserving their own separate country. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I can make out, the edits reverted are a mixture of vandalism and good-faith edits from users on both sides of the border, with many taking issue with him being referred to as just &#x27;Muhammad Iqbal&#x27; instead of a more respectful &#x27;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Allamah&quot;&gt;Allama&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; Muhammad Iqbal&#x27;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of growing interest in the UP elections can be seen by how from August to November, it was one of the pages most abused each month, impressive for an election whose dates haven&#x27;t even been announced yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;wikipedia-page-abuse&#x2F;politics_monthly.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Most abused Indian pages on Wikipedia each month -- Politics Pages&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s not only pages related to politics that get abused though. If we look outside politics, we see it&#x27;s pages about movies such as Bollywood film &#x27;Radhe&#x27; and Tamil film &#x27;Master&#x27; or shows such as &#x27;Indian Idol&#x27; and &#x27;Fear Factor&#x27; that experience the most vandalism. These edits may not be politically motivated, but the popularity of these movies and shows comes with a price as online mischief-makers flock to such pages.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if we look at the pages outside politics that were most abused each month, the entries tend to track the release schedule of major movies in Hindi and the southern languages. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;wikipedia-page-abuse&#x2F;nonpolitics_monthly.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Most abused Indian pages on Wikipedia each month -- Non-Politics Pages&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that wikipedia pages on movies face a lot of abuse isn&#x27;t terribly interesting though. Thanks to the Indian passion for films and cricket, the abuse these pages face is pretty much a given. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a little curious about how the graphic above would look like if we left out pages on movies as well as TV and sports. Just to see what other pages have been attracting attention from bad actors, and if there are any curious surprises that would spring up.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;wikipedia-page-abuse&#x2F;nonpolitics_monthly_no_movies_tv_sports.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Most abused Indian pages on Wikipedia each month -- Outside politics, movies, TV and sports&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at this new table, some of the entries are explainable, holidays or religious festivals appearing in the list for particular months such as Pahela Baisakh in April or Independence day in August. Other entries seem to be following the news cycle such as Gyanvapi Mosque in April and Cyclone Tauktae in May. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did find it interesting that articles on biryani and dosa were also abused. Looking into the page histories, it seems some disputed the origins of biryani in Muslim culinary traditions, some took issue with the article saying the word &#x27;biryani&#x27; is derived from Persian, and there were more petty edits like removing Pakistan from a list of countries where biryani is eaten.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the article on dosa, some abusive edits tried changing the spelling of &#x27;dosa&#x27; to &#x27;dosai&#x27; to match how it&#x27;s pronounced in some south indian states. Some argued over whether the oldest recipe for dosa is found in ancient Tamil or ancient Kannada literature, and others over whether it was Tamil or Udupi restaurants that first popularised the dosa in Mumbai. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-notes&quot;&gt;SIDE NOTES&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just putting some random thoughts here I couldn&#x27;t fit into the copy:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if we see what different reporters write as a unified body of knowledge, am I contributing to it or advancing it in any way with this post? That wikipedia abuse is happening isn&#x27;t a news point. It&#x27;s been happening for a long time, and the recent surge in India has been covered well by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.onmanorama.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;kerala&#x2F;2021&#x2F;08&#x2F;15&#x2F;onam-wikipedia-page-edit-wars-right-wing-mobs.amp.html&quot;&gt;Kuriakose&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;caravanmagazine.in&#x2F;media&#x2F;wikipedia-earned-ire-hindu-right&quot;&gt;Kauntia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I guess knowing that such and such page was abused the most in 2021 is kind of news-y. But this post isn&#x27;t really about advancing that body of knowledge or presenting ready-made insights to readers. It&#x27;s about informing people there&#x27;s a twitter account available that lets them keep an eye on wikipedia abuse in India, and which they can use to form insights of their own. So I&#x27;m being a little less hand hold-y here compared to a traditional journalist.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#x27;t know if there&#x27;ll be much interest in the topic of wikipedia abuse. Maybe not the general audience, but maybe people with an interest in wikipedia issues? Media researchers, casual contributors and the like? I don&#x27;t expect serious wikipedia editors to be using this though. First of all there&#x27;ll be at most a week&#x27;s lag between a page being abused and it appearing in the twitter graphics being put out. So it can&#x27;t be used as an early-warning system at all. Besides, serious editors have their own systems in place, and can create watchlists of pages to track within wikipedia itself. So yeah, I expect more of a niche audience for this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have decided to keep the indicator of abuse simple—number of users reverted on a page over a week or year. I could&#x27;ve gone through academic papers on wikipedia and borrowed a more sophisticated metric, but I think this is easier for people to grasp. I&#x27;ve done work in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijithpk.github.io&#x2F;world_cup_tourism&#x2F;index.html&quot;&gt;the past&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that tries to be conscientiously rigorous, but I don&#x27;t think journalism is the place for such work. Academic journals maybe, but not publications meant for the general public. In the pursuit of precision and conclusion validity, a lot of data journalism in India has become completely unreadable. I don&#x27;t think there&#x27;s anything wrong in admitting upfront that this post is a best-effort attempt, the conclusions may not be completely valid, but that hopefully this promotes the topic of wikipedia abuse in India as a legitimate avenue of research. And that some academic out there does a better job than I did in their paper. But I don&#x27;t think a journalist should be &lt;i&gt;the one&lt;&#x2F;i&gt; doing that paper.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more of a caveat. Some of these pages will have been placed under protection to stop getting abused. Protection could, for example, mean edits by anonymous users not appearing till they&#x27;re approved, or if someone has been a registered user for less than 4 days and has done less than 10 edits, they won&#x27;t be able to edit certain pages. The page on Narendra Modi is under even stricter protection—only someone who&#x27;s been a user for more than 30 days and has done over 500 edits can edit the page, and this has been the case since April. Such protections brings down the abuse levels for many pages, so that should be kept in mind.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now given the size of India&#x27;s internet userbase (over 600 million by one estimate), seeing just 215 users abuse a wikipedia page over a year doesn&#x27;t seem like much. But this is one of those situations that will get worse over the coming years as wikipedia attracts ever more attention from troll armies that form around various interests. So it may be interesting to keep an eye on it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m just looking at the English-language Wikipedia, but if anyone wants to use wikipedia abuse to gauge online discontent at a regional level, they should also look at Indian-language wikipedias and the abuse they experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;suggestions-feedback&quot;&gt;Suggestions, feedback&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are things here I should be doing differently, do let me know! Contact me at abuse_checker@shijith.com or at this Twitter handle &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;abuse_checker&quot;&gt;@abuse_checker&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Hide like counts on Twitter and karma points on Reddit with uBlock Origin</title>
        <published>2021-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2021-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://shijith.com/blog/hiding-like-upvote-counts/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://shijith.com/blog/hiding-like-upvote-counts/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post is about how I use the adblocker &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;gorhill&#x2F;uBlock&quot;&gt;uBlock Origin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to hide like&#x2F;retweet counts on Twitter, and karma points on Reddit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivation being that by removing all these stats social media pushes on you, you can have a better experience on these platforms and improve your digital wellbeing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To remove all the tweet&#x2F;post&#x2F;user stats, install uBlock Origin for your browser, copy the filters from this &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;hide_like_counts_with_ublock&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and paste it into the &#x27;My filters&#x27; section. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Pic of uBlock my filters section](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;i.imgur.com&#x2F;o4wkONX.jpg) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;hiding-like-upvote-counts&#x2F;reddit_0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pic of uBlock my filters section&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These filters are mainly for people who use Reddit and Twitter on their desktops, sorry mobile app users. It could be used on mobile with a Firefox-uBlock combo (Android) or Safari-AdGuard (iOS), but I haven&#x27;t tested them. The filters could be used in adblockers other than uBlock Origin, but you&#x27;ll have to check first.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-i-created-these-filters&quot;&gt;Why I created these filters&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial reason was to stop myself from getting upset over downvotes on Reddit. I&#x27;m particularly active on the subreddit for my home state, but saying anything unpopular has consequences with trolls downvoting your comment and bringing down your overall user &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;karma&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;index&#x2F;faq&#x2F;&quot;&gt;karma&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was angry about this in the beginning, but realised that I could either stop expressing my opinions to keep my karma from going down, or I could continue saying what I have to say. I decided to not censor myself, and do something so that others&#x27; downvotes don&#x27;t affect me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution I came up with was to use my adblocker to hide my user karma from my screen, and also hide how many downvotes my comments are getting. So the points become out of sight, out of mind and I don&#x27;t stress over them anymore.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a screenshot of a subreddit homepage where the vote count gets hidden after applying my filters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;hiding-like-upvote-counts&#x2F;reddit_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pic of a subreddit homepage before applying filters and after&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Pic of a subreddit homepage before applying filters and after](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;i.imgur.com&#x2F;Mh9XOi2.jpg) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this before and after screenshot, the vote count for comments under a post are hidden.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;hiding-like-upvote-counts&#x2F;reddit_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pic of how filters hide negative votes for a post&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!--  ![Pic of how filters hide negative votes for a post](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;i.imgur.com&#x2F;QatWQ4t.jpg) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that these filters still allow you to upvote or downvote posts or comments, so you can still engage with Reddit. Everything still works the same, just that the stats get hidden now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s not just the vote counts for your own posts&#x2F;comments that get hidden, but those of everyone else too. And I think this might be a better way of doing things. Your judgement of a post&#x27;s or comment&#x27;s worth will now not be dependent on how many votes it&#x27;s gotten, but only on whether you think it&#x27;s good or not.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;creating-filters-for-twitter&quot;&gt;Creating filters for Twitter&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing something similar for Twitter was kind of an afterthought. I didn&#x27;t really feel the need to do something for it like I did for Reddit. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I know that Instagram is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;about.instagram.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;announcements&#x2F;giving-people-more-control&quot;&gt;introducing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; the option to hide like counts for their posts. So, as an experiment, I wanted to experience what Twitter would be like without like and retweet counts, follower counts etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a before and after screenshot of NYT&#x27;s Twitter profile where the follower count gets hidden, as well as the blue tick.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Pic of follower account and blue ticks hidden by filters for NYT&#x27;s Twitter profile](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;i.imgur.com&#x2F;Mhmev43.jpg)--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;hiding-like-upvote-counts&#x2F;reddit_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pic of follower account and blue ticks hidden by filters for NYT&#x27;s Twitter profile&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a before and after screenshot for a tweet where the reply, retweet and like counts get hidden.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Pic of how filters hide reply, retweet and like counts for a tweet, before and after](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;i.imgur.com&#x2F;JXSqlsk.jpg) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;hiding-like-upvote-counts&#x2F;reddit_3B.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pic of how filters hide reply, retweet and like counts for a tweet, before and after&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the spirit of evaluating people&#x27;s tweets based purely on the content, I decided to remove blue ticks from the Twitter interface too, so that I didn&#x27;t look at tweets coming from verified handles more favourably. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Pic of how filters hide blue ticks for verified accounts, before and after for an NYT tweet](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;i.imgur.com&#x2F;3prMTVe.jpg)--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;hiding-like-upvote-counts&#x2F;reddit_3A.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pic of how filters hide blue ticks for verified accounts, before and after for an NYT tweet&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve browsed Twitter this way for a few weeks now, and while I don&#x27;t really miss the retweet&#x2F;like counts or the blue ticks, I do miss the reply count.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quality of replies to tweets can be pretty poor sometimes, but there&#x27;s always a few people in there with good insights. No reply counts means I don&#x27;t see which tweets are getting responses, so I don&#x27;t know which tweets I need to click on to get to those insights. The reply count is important for the way I use Twitter, so that&#x27;s something I&#x27;m considering keeping and not hiding.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also use Tweetdeck heavily, so there are filters in my list for Tweetdeck too. As with the main website Twitter.com, I&#x27;m considering unhiding the reply counts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Pic of reply, retweet and like stats being hidden for a tweet in Tweetdeck, before and after filters are applied](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;i.imgur.com&#x2F;Be28RKa.jpg) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;hiding-like-upvote-counts&#x2F;reddit_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pic of reply, retweet and like stats being hidden for a tweet in Tweetdeck, before and after filters are applied&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping up&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time you use these filters, the interfaces of these websites will look dramatically different. If there are any particular changes you want to undo, comment out the individual filter responsible in uBlock Origin. There&#x27;s a line above each filter explaining what it does.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if the layout of these websites change in a way that make these filters ineffective, I&#x27;ll keep the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;hide_like_counts_with_ublock&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; updated with working versions of these filters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can even set up your own filters to deal with annoyances on other websites. This &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=2lisQQmWQkY&quot;&gt;YouTube video&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a good intro to uBlock Origin and this &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;gorhill&#x2F;uBlock&#x2F;wiki&quot;&gt;wiki&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; goes into all the details.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter and Reddit may eventually introduce settings like Facebook and Instagram have to hide like&#x2F;vote counts, but till that happens, this &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;hide_like_counts_with_ublock&quot;&gt;filter list&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a handy option.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;suggestions-feedback&quot;&gt;Suggestions, feedback&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not a professional developer&#x2F;programmer&#x2F;coder, so am sure there are things here I should be doing differently. If you have any suggestions, please let me know at mail@shijith.com or at my Twitter handle &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;shijith&quot;&gt;@shijith&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I understand a filter will be more efficient, the smaller the initial set of nodes it goes through on a webpage. So if you have advice on optimising these filters even further, do let me know!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Making it easier to add users from one Twitter list to another</title>
        <published>2021-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2021-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://shijith.com/blog/twitter-list-management/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://shijith.com/blog/twitter-list-management/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post is about &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;twitter_list_mgmt&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;twitter_list_mgmt&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a python package I created to make it easier to add users to your Twitter list from other lists.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say you&#x27;ve created a covid twitter list to keep track of news around the pandemic. You&#x27;ve just found another list on covid curated by an epidemiologist in London, and you want to add members from that to your own Covid list. This is the package you use for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for most basic operations like retrieving the current membership of a Twitter list, adding users to it, removing them etc. the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;tweepy&#x2F;tweepy&quot;&gt;Tweepy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; library is good enough. &lt;code&gt;twitter_list_mgmt&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; just adds extra functionality on top of Tweepy to make working with lists easier.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This package will help heavy twitter and tweetdeck users, especially those who use lists to manage the firehose of information from social media.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;list-of-functions&quot;&gt;List of functions&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s what you can do with the &lt;code&gt;twitter_list_mgmt&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; package:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main functions
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add members to your list from another list &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#1&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add members to your list from multiple lists &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#2&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove members from your list who are in another list &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#3&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove members from your list who are in any of multiple other lists &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#4&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new list that combines members from multiple lists &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#5&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new list that has members common to multiple lists &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#6&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new list with members from a list, who aren&#x27;t in any of multiple other lists &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#7&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other functions
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the list id from a list url &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#8&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get all the user ids of list members &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#9&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add user ids to a list &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#10&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove user ids from a list &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#11&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a pandas dataframe from a list &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;twitter-list-management&#x2F;.&#x2F;#12&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-install-the-package-and-set-things-up&quot;&gt;How to install the package and set things up&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Versions of Tweepy &amp;gt;= 4.0.0a0 are required for this package to work. At the time of writing, 4.0.0 is not available in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pypi.org&#x2F;project&#x2F;tweepy&#x2F;#history&quot;&gt;pypi&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Install it from the terminal by doing&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;pip install git+https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;tweepy&#x2F;tweepy.git
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of setting up, you&#x27;ll have to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;developer.twitter.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;create&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; authentication credentials for yourself. (This &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;realpython.com&#x2F;twitter-bot-python-tweepy&#x2F;&quot;&gt;article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from Realpython has a how-to on it.) Four text strings will be generated -- Consumer Key, Consumer Secret, Access Token and Access Token Secret. Create a file named &#x27;config_twitter.ini&#x27;, use the format below and paste in the credentials without apostrophes. You can also download a sample file &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;twitter_list_mgmt&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;twitter_list_mgmt&#x2F;config_twitter.ini&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Place the config in the same directory and on the same level as your script.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;[info]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;CONSUMER_KEY = XXXXXX
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;CONSUMER_SECRET = XXXXXX
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;ACCESS_TOKEN = XXXXXX
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;ACCESS_TOKEN_SECRET = XXXXXX
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then install the main package by going to the terminal and typing&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;pip install twitter_list_mgmt
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-use-the-package&quot;&gt;How to use the package&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Import the package into your code with&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;import twitter_list_mgmt as tlm
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package has &lt;strong&gt;7&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; main functions:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add members to your list from another list&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Here &#x27;list1&#x27; and &#x27;list2&#x27; are twitter list ids, with list1 being the one you own. (You can get the ids from the url for a list page. For example, in the url &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;i&#x2F;lists&#x2F;15299140&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;i&#x2F;lists&#x2F;15299140&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, the list id is &#x27;15299140&#x27;.)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.add_to_list1_from_list2(list1, list2)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add members to your list from several other lists&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — &#x27;multiple_lists&#x27; is a python list of twitter list ids. (To comply with Twitter&#x27;s rate limits, only upto 1000 members can be added in a day.)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.add_to_list1_from_multiple_lists(list1, 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                            multiple_lists)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove members from your list who are in another list&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Let&#x27;s say you have a twitter list on covid that&#x27;s a mix of experts and journalists, and you want it to have experts only. Now you can remove many of the journalists from it manually, but you can also do it in an automated fashion by getting a list of science&#x2F;health journalists. Using this function, if any of your list members are on that journalist list, they&#x27;ll be removed. &#x27;list1&#x27; here is your list id.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.remove_from_list1_based_on_list2(list1, list2)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove members from your list who are in any of the other lists specified&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — &#x27;list1&#x27; here is your list id and &#x27;multiple_lists&#x27; is a python list of twitter list ids.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.remove_from_list1_based_on_multiple_lists(list1,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                    multiple_lists)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a new list that combines members from several lists&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — &#x27;multiple_lists&#x27; is the python list containing the twitter list ids and &#x27;list_name&#x27; is the name for the new list. (The Twitter list created is set as &#x27;private&#x27; but can be made &#x27;public&#x27; later.)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.create_list_union(multiple_lists,list_name)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a new list that has members common to several lists&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — &#x27;multiple_lists&#x27; is the python list containing the twitter list ids and &#x27;list_name&#x27; is the name for the new list.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.create_list_intersection(multiple_lists,list_name)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;7&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a new list with all the members from a list, who aren&#x27;t in any of the other lists specified&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — &#x27;list1&#x27; can be your own list or someone else&#x27;s, &#x27;multiple_lists&#x27; is a python list of twitter list ids and &#x27;list_name&#x27; is the name for the new list.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.create_list_difference(list1,multiple_lists,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                    list_name)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-things-you-can-do&quot;&gt;Other things you can do&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The functions that have been listed are the main ones. There are others too, but most people won&#x27;t need them. Will go through some of those functions for coders who want to build something on top of them. (Go through &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;twitter_list_mgmt&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;twitter_list_mgmt&#x2F;helpers.py&quot;&gt;helpers.py&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in the github repo to see how they&#x27;ve been defined.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the other functions:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;8&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get the list id from a list url&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Extracts the list_id and returns it as a string.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.get_list_id_from_url(url)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;9&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get all the members of a list&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — The function returns a python list of their user ids.  Tweepy has a similar function &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;docs.tweepy.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;latest&#x2F;api.html#tweepy.API.get_list_members&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;get_list_members&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; but that retrieves user objects. This function goes a step further by extracting the user ids within those objects.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.get_list_members_ids(list_idx)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;10&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add user ids to a list&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — &#x27;ids&#x27; here is a python list of user ids and &#x27;list1&#x27; is a twitter list id.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.add_ids_to_list(ids,list1)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;11&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove user ids from a list&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — &#x27;ids&#x27; here is a python list of user ids and &#x27;list1&#x27; is a twitter list id.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.remove_ids_from_list(ids,list1)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;12&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a pandas dataframe from a list&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — Here, each row is for a different member and each column an attribute like number of followers, number of tweets posted etc. This is for anyone who wants to analyze the membership of a list.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;tlm.create_df_from_list(list_idx)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;suggestions-criticism-etc&quot;&gt;Suggestions, criticism etc.&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not a professional developer&#x2F;programmer&#x2F;coder, so am sure there are things here I should be doing differently. If you have any suggestions, please contact me on mail@shijith.com or at my twitter handle &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;shijith&quot;&gt;@shijith&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I would be interested in hearing about my python application layout. Whether it could be simplified further, if I could be doing imports better etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Finding new music on Spotify by aggregating the choices of tastemakers</title>
        <published>2021-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2021-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://shijith.com/blog/automating-music-discovery/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://shijith.com/blog/automating-music-discovery/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m an amateur python coder and I write here about trying to make it easier to find new music. I do this by essentially combining playlists from influential music websites and radio stations into a single one on Spotify. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have decided to do this and not use Spotify&#x27;s human-curated and algorithmic playlists because they lack authority for me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simple python script I&#x27;ve written for aggregating playlists is in this &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;music-discovery&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#x27;t want to code anything and just want the music, you have two options:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;open.spotify.com&#x2F;playlist&#x2F;0kqXhlpDiRbab64ip8g8Ap&quot;&gt;demo playlist&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; created using the default choices.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;open.spotify.com&#x2F;playlist&#x2F;3XidTKBIpsGymPCjlN7kZH&quot;&gt;personal playlist&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that mines 33 sources of new music.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-earlier-routine-for-finding-music&quot;&gt;My earlier routine for finding music&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to finding new music, my usual sources were Spotify playlists, online radio streams and YouTube channels. I love music, but going through each of them is difficult to do every week. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having to visit each individual website, realizing that &amp;quot;Oh, I didn&#x27;t go to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;livesessions.npr.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;NPR Live Sessions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; last week, so got to do it this week&amp;quot;. The very fact that I call it a &#x27;routine&#x27; shows how it had become a chore for me, a sequence of steps to follow every week. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&#x27;ve decided to simplify my music discovery process, and make it less of a &#x27;routine&#x27; by collecting all the new music I should be listening to in one Spotify playlist. Reduce those multiple steps into a single one, stick to that one playlist and be happy with that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&#x27;ve done is I&#x27;ve mined various playlists on Spotify that look at the new music that&#x27;s released every week. These playlists are from radio stations like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.kcrw.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;KCRW&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and BBC &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;automating-music-discovery&#x2F;bbc.co.uk&#x2F;6music&quot;&gt;Radio 6&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, music websites like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pitchfork.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Pitchfork&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.thelineofbestfit.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Line of Best Fit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and traditional publications like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.rollingstone.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Rolling Stone&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;automating-music-discovery&#x2F;logos_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Logos of music tastemakers&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are stations, websites and publications that care about music and are considered tastemakers in the US and UK. And by aggregating their choices, I get to benefit from their collective musical wisdom in one playlist without investing hours of my time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-i-m-not-using-spotify-s-own-playlists&quot;&gt;Why I&#x27;m not using Spotify&#x27;s own playlists&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re a Spotify obsessive, you could point out that it has its own playlists, human-curated ones like &#x27;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;open.spotify.com&#x2F;playlist&#x2F;37i9dQZF1DX4JAvHpjipBk&quot;&gt;New Music Friday&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x27; and algorithmic ones like &#x27;Release Radar&#x27; that specifically look at the new music released in the week. So why reinvent the wheel?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is the websites and stations whose playlists I&#x27;m aggregating are widely respected. I may not like some of the songs these tastemakers recommend, but it&#x27;s important for me to hear these recommendations and then maybe reject them, than to never hear them at all.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were also part of my routine earlier, so it&#x27;s important to me that they remain part of my music discovery process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No doubt, Spotify&#x27;s own playlists are very &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theguardian.com&#x2F;music&#x2F;2019&#x2F;apr&#x2F;28&#x2F;streaming-music-algorithms-spotify&quot;&gt;influential&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and the curators behind them have become minor &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edmreviewer.com&#x2F;2020&#x2F;04&#x2F;20&#x2F;austin-kramer-the-god-of-edm&#x2F;&quot;&gt;celebrities&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in their own right. But since these playlists aren&#x27;t from established sources of musical authority or from institutions I&#x27;m familiar with, I value their judgement a little less.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-you-want-to-rely-less-on-spotify-s-algorithms&quot;&gt;If you want to rely less on Spotify&#x27;s algorithms&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I&#x27;m not exactly a &#x27;down with algorithms&#x27; guy.  If your issue with Spotify&#x27;s algorithmic playlists is that there is a sameness to the music, that you&#x27;re not getting exposed to different artists, and you fear you&#x27;ll end up in a musical &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;LetsTalkMusic&#x2F;comments&#x2F;g8m4m2&#x2F;spotify_radio_from_song_or_album_is_it_just_me_or&#x2F;&quot;&gt;filter bubble&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, my feeling is these issues are correctable. The algorithms can be tweaked to make Spotify&#x27;s recommendations more diverse. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you&#x27;ve made up your mind about Spotify and want to rely less on its algorithms, you can use the script I&#x27;ve put up on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;music-discovery&quot;&gt;Github&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to generate musically varied playlists.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m aggregating playlists from tastemakers in my script, but you can collect playlists from any user you find on Spotify. It doesn&#x27;t have to just be for new music either. For example, you could aggregate acoustic music playlists from various users to get a new acoustic playlist every week.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gap-this-tool-fills&quot;&gt;The gap this tool fills&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet isn&#x27;t short of playlist creation tools for Spotify. The thing is most of them are &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;dubolt.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;about&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; generating playlists of music based on a song or artist you seed it with. Or generating playlists based on a &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;playlistminer.playlistmachinery.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;keyword&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This script tries to do something different by generating a playlist based on your choice of musical authority. And also update it every week, once you schedule it that way. For most tools (with one &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mixtapemanager.ca&#x2F;&quot;&gt;exception&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), playlist generation is a one-time exercise with no updates.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One website that tries to aggregate tastemaker preferences like this is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hypem.com&quot;&gt;Hype Machine&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It collects recommendations from hundreds of music websites, blogs etc. and has its own interface for listening to music. The thing is, for many people their musical world is centred around Spotify and Apple Music, but Hype Machine isn&#x27;t integrated with those apps.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hypem.com&#x2F;latest&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;automating-music-discovery&#x2F;hypemachine.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Hype Machine&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-it-s-implemented&quot;&gt;How it&#x27;s implemented&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There isn&#x27;t anything sophisticated being done here, it&#x27;s just a python script. But hopefully this will meet the needs of &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;amateur coders who want to spend less time finding new music&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lifehackers who want to automate aspects of their lives and, &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in general, anyone who wants to simplify their Spotify experience.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 75 playlists users can choose to aggregate. They&#x27;re all new music playlists, updated every week&#x2F;month, from important music publications, websites and radio stations in the US and UK. While most of the playlists explore new music across genres, some are genre-specific, some focus on new music from emerging artists, while others focus on tracks from new albums. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 playlists (from Pitchfork, Rolling Stone, KCRW in the US and Line of Best Fit, NME, BBC Radio 6 in the UK) have been pre-selected to give a user default choices to start with, but they can be un-selected.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you follow the instructions in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;music-discovery&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, you&#x27;ll end up with a playlist titled &#x27;New Music for &amp;lt; your Spotify user id &amp;gt;&#x27; in your Spotify library.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A demo playlist created using the six default choices is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;open.spotify.com&#x2F;playlist&#x2F;0kqXhlpDiRbab64ip8g8Ap&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;open.spotify.com&#x2F;playlist&#x2F;0kqXhlpDiRbab64ip8g8Ap&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shijith.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;automating-music-discovery&#x2F;playlist_screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of spotify playlist&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;don-t-turn-music-into-work&quot;&gt;Don&#x27;t turn music into work&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that your playlist is wiped clean and new tracks are added every time you run the script. So you&#x27;ll need to get through the songs on the playlist before you run the script again. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#x27;t have to make it a chore though, or get anxious about finishing the playlist. Just have it running in the background while you&#x27;re working or browsing, &#x27;like&#x27; songs to add them to your liked songs list, and skip liberally. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theverge.com&#x2F;2020&#x2F;5&#x2F;26&#x2F;21270409&#x2F;spotify-song-library-limit-removed-music-downloads-playlists-feature&quot;&gt;no limit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in Spotify to how many songs you can like. You can then decide later what you want to do with your liked songs. Put some on a workout playlist, others on an office playlist etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-more-details&quot;&gt;For more details&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code, and more details about the implementation are available in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;music-discovery&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this tool will give people a model to build on, and create even better setups for finding new music.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>About me</title>
        <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://shijith.com/about/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://shijith.com/about/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-me&quot;&gt;About me&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi, my name&#x27;s Shijith Kunhitty, and I&#x27;m a data journalist based in India. I&#x27;m on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;shijith&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.linkedin.com&#x2F;in&#x2F;shijith&#x2F;&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;shijithpk&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Github&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. But the best way to contact me is over email, my id is &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mail@shijith.com&quot;&gt;mail@shijith.com&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- Not looking for work at the moment, but I definitely want to do something once the pandemic&#x27;s over. If you&#x27;re in the Indian media and hiring for roles combining journalism and coding, here&#x27;s my [resume](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.dropbox.com&#x2F;s&#x2F;9h55igvtgm3ztcy&#x2F;shijith_resume_may_2021.pdf?dl=1). --&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
</feed>
